//References
let timeLeft = document.querySelector(".time-left");
let quizContainer = document.getElementById("container");
let nextBtn = document.getElementById("next-button");
let countOfQuestion = document.querySelector(".number-of-question");
let displayContainer = document.getElementById("display-container");
let scoreContainer = document.querySelector(".score-container");
let restart = document.getElementById("restart");
let userScore = document.getElementById("user-score");
let startScreen = document.querySelector(".start-screen");
let startButton = document.getElementById("start-button");
let questionCount;
let scoreCount = 0;
let count = 30;
let countdown;

//hide quiz and display start screen
window.onload = () => {
  startScreen.classList.remove("hide");
  displayContainer.classList.add("hide");
};

//Questions and Options array

const quizArray = [
   
  {
    id: "26",
    question: "What is a correct syntax to output \"Hello World\" in Java?",
    options: [
      "System.out.println(\"Hello World\");",
      "print (\"Hello World\");",
      "Console.WriteLine(\"Hello World\");",
      "echo(\"Hello World\");"
    ],
    correct: "System.out.println(\"Hello World\");"
  },
  {
    id: "27",
    question: "Java is short for \"JavaScript\".",
    options: [
      "False",
      "True"
    ],
    correct: "False"
  },
  {
    id: "28",
    question: "How do you insert COMMENTS in Java code?",
    options: [
      "// This is a comment",
      "/* This is a comment",
      "# This is a comment"
    ],
    correct: "// This is a comment"
  },
  {
    id: "29",
    question: "Which data type is used to create a variable that should store text?",
    options: [
      "String",
      "myString",
      "string",
      "Txt"
    ],
    correct: "String"
  },
  {
    id: "30",
    question: "How do you create a variable with the numeric value 5?",
    options: [
      "int x = 5;",
      "float x = 5;",
      "x = 5;",
      "num x = 5"
    ],
    correct: "int x = 5;"
  },
  {
    id: "31",
    question: "How do you create a variable with the floating number 2.8?",
    options: [
      "float x = 2.8f;",
      "int x = 2.8f;",
      "x = 2.8f;",
      "byte x = 2.8f"
    ],
    correct: "float x = 2.8f;"
  },
  {
    id: "32",
    question: "Which method can be used to find the length of a string?",
    options: [
      "getLength()",
      "len()",
      "length()",
      "getSize()"
    ],
    correct: "length()"
  },
  {
    id: "33",
    question: "Which operator is used to add together two values?",
    options: [
      "The + sign",
      "The & sign",
      "The * sign"
    ],
    correct: "The + sign"
  },
  {
    id: "34",
    question: "The value of a string variable can be surrounded by single quotes.",
    options: [
      "False",
      "True"
    ],
    correct: "False"
  },
  {
    id: "35",
    question: "Which method can be used to return a string in upper case letters?",
    options: [
      "toUpperCase()",
      "touppercase()",
      "tuc()",
      "upperCase()"
    ],
    correct: "toUpperCase()"
  },
  {
    id: "36",
    question: "Which operator can be used to compare two values?",
    options: [
      "==",
      "<>",
      "=",
      "><"
    ],
    correct: "=="
  },
  {
    id: "37",
    question: "To declare an array in Java, define the variable type with:",
    options: [
      "[]",
      "{}",
      "()"
    ],
    correct: "[]"
  },
  {
    id: "38",
    question: "Array indexes start with:",
    options: [
      "0",
      "1"
    ],
    correct: "0"
  },
  {
    id: "39",
    question: "How do you create a method in Java?",
    options: [
      "methodName()",
      "methodName[]",
      "methodName."
    ],
    correct: "methodName()"
  },
  {
    id: "40",
    question: "How do you call a method in Java?",
    options: [
      "methodName();",
      "methodName;",
      "methodName[]",
      "(methodName);"
    ],
    correct: "methodName();"
  },
  {
    id: "41",
    question: "Which keyword is used to create a class in Java?",
    options: [
      "class",
      "MyClass",
      "className",
      "class()"
    ],
    correct: "class"
  },
  {
    id: "42",
    question: "What is the correct way to create an object called myObj of MyClass?",
    options: [
      "class MyClass = new myObj();",
      "new myObj = MyClass();",
      "MyClass myObj = new MyClass();",
      "class myObj = new MyClass();"
    ],
    correct: "MyClass myObj = new MyClass();"
  },
  {
    id: "43",
    question: "In Java, it is possible to inherit attributes and methods from one class to another.",
    options: [
      "True",
      "False"
    ],
    correct: "True"
  },
  {
    id: "44",
    question: "Which method can be used to find the highest value of x and y?",
    options: [
      "Math.max(x,y)",
      "Math.maxNum(x,y)",
      "Math.largest(x,y)",
      "Math.maximum(x,y)"
    ],
    correct: "Math.max(x,y)"
  },
  {
    id: "45",
    question: "Which operator is used to multiply numbers?",
    options: [
      "*",
      "x",
      "#",
      "%"
    ],
    correct: "*"
  },
  {
    id: "46",
    question: "Which keyword is used to import a package from the Java API library?",
    options: [
      "import",
      "getlib",
      "lib",
      "package"
    ],
    correct: "import"
  },
  {
    id: "47",
    question: "How do you start writing an if statement in Java?",
    options: [
      "if (x > y)",
      "if x > y:",
      "if x > y then:"
    ],
    correct: "if (x > y)"
  },
  {
    id: "48",
    question: "How do you start writing a while loop in Java?",
    options: [
      "while (x > y)",
      "x > y while {",
      "while x > y {",
      "while x > y:"
    ],
    correct: "while (x > y)"
  },
  {
    id: "49",
    question: "Which keyword is used to return a value inside a method?",
    options: [
      "return",
      "break",
      "void",
      "get"
    ],
    correct: "return"
  },
  {
    id: "50",
    question: "Which statement is used to stop a loop?",
    options: [
      "break",
      "stop",
      "exit",
      "return"
    ],
    correct: "break"
  },
];

//Restart Quiz
restart.addEventListener("click", () => {
  initial();
  displayContainer.classList.remove("hide");
  scoreContainer.classList.add("hide");
});

nextBtn.addEventListener(
  "click",
  (displayNext = () => {
    //increment questionCount
    questionCount += 1;
    //if last question
    if (questionCount == quizArray.length) {
      // Stop the timer
      clearInterval(countdown);

      // Hide the question container and display the score container
      displayContainer.classList.add("hide");
      scoreContainer.classList.remove("hide");

      // User score
      userScore.innerHTML =
        "You got " +
        scoreCount +
        " questions correct out of " +
        questionCount +
        " questions.";
    } else {
      // Display questionCount
      countOfQuestion.innerHTML =
        questionCount + 1 + " of " + quizArray.length + " Questions";
      // Display quiz
      quizDisplay(questionCount);
      count = 30;
      clearInterval(countdown);
      timerDisplay();
    }

    // Calculate percentage
    let answeredQuestions = questionCount;
    let totalQuestions = quizArray.length;
    let percentage = Math.floor((scoreCount / answeredQuestions) * 100);
    // Set default value to 0% if no questions answered
    percentage = isNaN(percentage) ? 0 : percentage;
    document.querySelector(".percentage").innerHTML = percentage + "%";

    // Display appraisal message based on percentage
    let appraisalHeading = document.getElementById("appraise-heading");
    if (percentage <= 50) {
      appraisalHeading.innerHTML = "Failed!";
    } else if (percentage <= 60) {
      appraisalHeading.innerHTML = "Above average!";
    } else if (percentage <= 80) {
      appraisalHeading.innerHTML = "Good job!";
    } else if (percentage <= 99) {
      appraisalHeading.innerHTML = "Excellent!";
    } else {
      appraisalHeading.innerHTML = "Perfect!";
    }
  })
);

//Timer
const timerDisplay = () => {
  countdown = setInterval(() => {
    count--;
    timeLeft.innerHTML = `${count}s`;
    if (count == 0) {
      clearInterval(countdown);
      displayNext();
    }
  }, 1000);
};

//Display quiz
const quizDisplay = (questionCount) => {
  let quizCards = document.querySelectorAll(".container-mid");
  //Hide other cards
  quizCards.forEach((card) => {
    card.classList.add("hide");
  });
  //display current question card
  quizCards[questionCount].classList.remove("hide");
};

//Quiz Creation
function quizCreator() {
  //randomly sort questions
  quizArray.sort(() => Math.random() - 0.5);
  //generate quiz
  for (let i of quizArray) {
    //randomly sort options
    i.options.sort(() => Math.random() - 0.5);
    //quiz card creation
    let div = document.createElement("div");
    div.classList.add("container-mid", "hide");
    //question number
    countOfQuestion.innerHTML = 1 + " of " + quizArray.length + " Questions";
    //question
    let question_DIV = document.createElement("p");
    question_DIV.classList.add("question");
    question_DIV.innerHTML = i.question;
    div.appendChild(question_DIV);
    //options
    div.innerHTML += `
    <button class="option-div" onclick="checker(this)">${i.options[0]}</button>
     <button class="option-div" onclick="checker(this)">${i.options[1]}</button>
      <button class="option-div" onclick="checker(this)">${i.options[2]}</button>
       <button class="option-div" onclick="checker(this)">${i.options[3]}</button>
    `;
    quizContainer.appendChild(div);
  }
}

// Checker Function to check if option is correct or not
function checker(userOption) {
  let userSolution = userOption.innerText;
  let question =
    document.getElementsByClassName("container-mid")[questionCount];
  let options = question.querySelectorAll(".option-div");

  // Decode the correct option
  let decodedCorrectOption = decodeEntities(quizArray[questionCount].correct);

  // If user clicked answer matches the decoded correct option
  if (userSolution === decodedCorrectOption) {
    userOption.classList.add("correct");
    scoreCount++;
  } else {
    userOption.classList.add("incorrect");
    // For marking the correct option
    options.forEach((element) => {
      if (element.innerText == decodedCorrectOption) {
        element.classList.add("correct");
      }
    });
  }

  // Clear interval (stop timer)
  clearInterval(countdown);
  // Disable all options
  options.forEach((element) => {
    element.disabled = true;
  });
}

// Function to decode HTML entities
function decodeEntities(encodedString) {
  const textarea = document.createElement("textarea");
  textarea.innerHTML = encodedString;
  return textarea.value;
}

//initial setup
function initial() {
  quizContainer.innerHTML = "";
  questionCount = 0;
  scoreCount = 0;
  count = 30;
  clearInterval(countdown);
  timerDisplay();
  quizCreator();
  quizDisplay(questionCount);
}

//when user click on start button
startButton.addEventListener("click", () => {
  startScreen.classList.add("hide");
  displayContainer.classList.remove("hide");
  initial();
});
